A Guide to the Papers of Edward E. Younger, 1942-1979
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Edward E. Younger 1942-1979
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
12742-a
This collection consists of ca. 425 items (3 Hollinger boxes, ca. 1.3 linear shelf feet).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Access restrictions apply under the terms of the Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (F.E.R.P.A.).
Acquisition Information
The Edward E. Younger papers were a gift of Mrs. Edward E. Younger of Crozet, Virginia on 1981 October 14.
Scope and Content Information
This lot of the papers of Edward E. Younger consists of ca. 425 items (3 Hollinger boxes, ca. 1.3 linear shelf feet), 1942-1979, relating to Younger's naval services and his tenure as professor of American History and chairman of the department at the University of Virginia. The collection is divided into four series: Correspondence, Topical Files, Student Papers, and Non-student Papers.
Contents List
- Correspondence
  - Correspondence 1965-1979, n.d., 111 items. 2 folders (Box 1)
- Topical Files
  - Daily Memorandum Book 1962-1979, 1 item. (Box 1)
  - Lecture: "American Attitudes Toward Foreign Policy in the 19th Century" by Edward E. Younger [1958 Jan 23], 1 item. (Box 1)
  - Letters of Recommendation (Restricted) 1969-1975, 11 items (Box 1)
  - John Hammond Moore re Australia and New Guinea 1970-1971, 2 items (Box 1)
  - Oceanic Education 1973-1974, 17 items (Box 1)
  - Retirement: Correspondence and Related Papers 1978, 40 items (Box 1)
  - United States: Correspondence and Related Papers 1978, 176 items. 2 folders (Box 1)
  - University of Virginia Cemetery [1976], 11 items (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous n.d., 13 items (Box 2)
  - Letter and Photographs sent to Hilton Robertson 1944 Oct 20, n.d., 7 items (Box 2)
  - Newsclippings and Printed Material 1955-1976, n.d., 20 items (Box 2)
- Student Papers
  - Aliamo, Peter Anthony, Jr.: "The Venezulean-British Guianan Boundary Dispute: Diplomatic Crisis or Press Event?" 1976 Apr, 1 item. (Box 2)
  - Cotton, Curtis re the efforts of Carter Godwin Woodson in popularizing the history of black people in America n.d., 1 item. (Box 2)
  - Fitzpatrick, Peter B.: "The Trescot Mission: A Failure in American Diplomacy" 1970 Jan 12, 1 item. (Box 2)
  - Fry, Joseph A. and Tartar, Brent: "Redemption of the Fighting Ninth" n.d., 1 item. (Box 2)
  - Horn, Herman L.: "The Growth and Development of the Democratic Party in Virginia Since 1890" 1949, 1 item. 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Laird, Julie: "John Marshall Harlan's Doctrine of Legal Equality" n.d., 1 item. (Box 2)
  - Martin, Lewis Ashby, III: "John A. G. Davis, Professor of Law, and the Faculty of the University of Virginia, 1830-1840" 1974 Aug, 1 item. (Box 2)
  - Pincus, Samuel N.: "Negroes on Juries in Post-Reconstruction Virginia: The Rives Case" 1970, 1 item. (Box 3)
  - Protos, George M.: "Virginia Governorship: A Study of the 'Underwood Constitution'" 1975 Apr 29, 1 item. (Box 3)
  - Saunders, Robert M.: "Richmond's Ruling Elite: Principles and Practices from the Revolution to the Civil War" 1975 Jul 18, 1 item. (Box 3)
  - Shi, David E.: "Matthew Josephson and the "Skyscraper Primitives': Broom Magazine, 1921-24" 1975 Apr 30, May 18, 2 items (Box 3)
  - Smith, Gilbert, III: "Richard Evelyn Byrd: Insurgent?" 1972 May 16, 2 items (Box 3)
  - [?]: "James Monroe in Albemarle County" n.d., 1 item. (Box 3)
- Non-Student Papers
  - Joseph A. Fry: Article, "Washington''s Farewell Address and American Commerce" 1976, 2 items
  - Robert T. Hawkes, Jr.: Article, "The Gubernatorial Administration of Harry Flood Byrd, 1926-1930: Efficiency and Economy in State Government" 1974 Apr 2, 1 item. (Box 3)
  - William E. Leverette and David E. Shi: Article, "Ralph Borsodi's Middle Class Middle Landscape" n.d., 1 item (Box 3)
  - Patrick Reed: "Fairfax: Phoenix or Failure (1870-1900)/The Electric Connection (1900-1925)" 1976 Jan 20, 1 item (Box 3)
  - David E. Shi: "Matthew Josephson-Bourgeois Bohemian" and related correspondence 1978, 4 items (Box 3)
  - David E. Shi: Article re William H. Seward n.d., 1 item. (Box 3)